Dorothy Dehner
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Dorothy Dehner papers
1920-1987 (bulk 1951-1987)
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Dorothy Dehner
4.4 linear feet
The papers of Dorothy Dehner measure approximately 4.4 linear feet and date from 1920 to 1987, with the bulk of the material dating from 1951 to 1987. The collection documents the life and work of the sculptor. Papers include extensive correspondence, business and financial papers, writings, interviews, printed material, photographs, student papers, one item of art work, and scattered personal papers and material relating to David Smith.
Biographical Note
Dorothy Dehner was born in Cleveland, Ohio in 1901. Her father died when she was about ten and the family moved to Pasadena, California in 1915. After the death of her mother and sister, she was raised by her mother's sister, Aunt Florence. Dehner was exposed to art as a child, receiving instruction in drawing and painting. She studied drama for a year at UCLA in 1922-1923 before moving to New York with the intention of pursuing a theatrical career. In 1925, she traveled alone to Europe, where she visited Italy, Switzerland, and France and where she began to draw seriously.
Upon her return to New York, Dehner enrolled in the Art Students League intending to study sculpture, but, uninspired by the work of William Zorach's sculpture class, ended up studying drawing with Kimon Nicolaides instead. In 1926, she met fellow artist David Smith in the rooming house they shared. At her suggestion, he too enrolled in the Art Students League. In 1927, they were married.
At the League, Dehner and Smith studied with the modernist painter, Jan Matulka, and befriended Weber and Thomas Furlong, through whom they met the Russian painter and theoretician, John Graham. Graham introduced them to the avant-garde art world and ended up having a profound influence on them both and their work. Around this time, they also befriended other young artists, such as Adolph Gottlieb, Mark Rothko, and Edgar and Lucille Corcos Levy. In 1929, after a visit to the Furlong's summer home in upstate New York, Dehner and Smith bought a farm in Bolton Landing, which became their permanent home in 1940 and was later named Terminal Iron Works. They spent eight months in the Virgin Islands, in 1931-1932, where Dehner painted abstract still lifes of shells and marine life. In the fall of 1935, they traveled to Europe, where they met up with Graham in Paris, spent five months in Greece, and toured the Soviet Union, with other stops along the way.
During her years at Bolton Landing (from 1940 to 1950), Dehner progressed in her work, producing a series of paintings titled Life on the Farm and embarking upon a series of abstract geometric drawings in ink and watercolor. In 1943, she had a joint exhibition with Smith at the Albany Institute of History and Art. Three years later, she participated in the annual exhibition of Audubon Artists and was awarded a first prize for drawing; and in 1948, she had her first one-woman show at Skidmore College.
Dehner left Bolton Landing in 1950 (she was divorced from Smith two years later) and returned to school, earning her degree from Skidmore College in 1952. She moved back to New York City, and supported herself over the next several years by teaching at various schools, including the Barnard School for Girls. She had her first solo exhibition in the city at the Rose Fried Gallery, and studied engraving at Stanley William Hayter's Atelier 17. At this point, Dehner started making sculpture, first experimenting in wax and then casting her wax sculptures in bronze. In 1955, she began working at the Sculpture Center, and from this point on, focused mainly on sculpture with occasional forays in drawing and print-making. In addition to works in bronze, she went on to create sculptures in wood (during the 1970s) and steel (during the 1980s).
In 1955, Dehner married the New York publisher, Ferdinand Mann. That same year, she joined the Willard Gallery, run by Marian Willard. She had her first exhibition of drawings there in 1955 (which led to a solo exhibition at the Art Institute of Chicago) and her first sculpture show there in 1957; she continued to show at the Willard Gallery regularly until 1976. Over the next several decades, Dehner's work was frequently exhibited in solo and groups shows at museums and galleries across the country, and was acquired for both public and private collections.
In addition to her art work, Dehner was also a published poet and writer. She wrote the foreword to the 1971 re-issue of John Graham's System and Dialectics of Art, and an essay on David Smith's "Medals for Dishonor," which was published in Art Journal in 1977. And two of her poems, "Past Tense" and "Two Lines," appeared in the journal Tracks in 1977.
Dehner continued to work into her nineties. She passed away in 1994.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Dorothy Dehner measure approximately 4.4 linear feet and date from 1920 to 1987, with the bulk of the material dating from 1951 to 1987. The collection documents the life and work of the sculptor. Papers include extensive correspondence, business and financial papers, writings, interviews, printed material, photographs, student papers, one item of art work, and scattered personal papers and material relating to David Smith.
Comprising a series of biographical material are interviews (mostly untranscribed), personal papers such as notes on Dehner's biography and career, list of things taken from Bolton Landing, recipes, and a wedding announcement for her stepdaughter, Abby Mann Thernstrom, and material relating to David Smith such as a copy of his last will and testament, a letter of introduction (dating from their trip to Europe in the mid-1930s), and a chronology of Smith's life.
Correspondence consists of numerous letters and enclosures concerning both professional and personal matters. Correspondents include artists, museums, galleries, art dealers, researchers, curators, friends, and relatives. Correspondence documents Dehner's various personal and professional relationships, the active role she played in promoting and exhibiting her art work, as well as the key role she played in fostering art historical research (on David Smith, herself, and other artists of her era), and her many other creative activities, including her various writing efforts.
Found amongst Dehner's business and financial papers are records relating to various galleries and/or exhibitions, including the Willard Gallery and exhibitions at the Philadelphia Art Alliance and Parsons-Dreyfuss Gallery, and to various projects, such as the Committee for the American Participation in the Triennale and the Great Southwest Industrial Park, as well as scattered records relating to personal business matters and finances, such as lists, tax records, authentication of art works, and sales agreements.
Dehner's writings include poems (including one dated from high school and drafts of ones published in Tracks), various pieces on John Graham (including versions of a memoir, which were published as a foreword to the re-issue of System and Dialectics of Art and as an article in Leonardo) and on David Smith (including articles on their first meeting and on Smith's 1940 work, "Medals for Dishonor"), lectures and speeches, and various pieces on art and other topics. Writings shed light on other aspects of Dehner's creativity and concern. Also included are writings of others, some of which shed light on Dehner's life and work.
Also found amongst Dehner's papers are printed material, including exhibition catalogs, announcements, and clippings (on herself and Smith, and to a limited extent, on other artists); an undated etching by Dehner which seems to have originally belong to Garnett McCoy, former Curator of the Archives; and photographs of Dehner, her second husband, Ferdinand Mann, John Graham, and various works of art, as well as an abstract photograph by David Smith, dating from circa 1934.
Arrangement
The Dorothy Dehner papers are arranged into 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1935-1982 (bulk 1950s-1982) (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1927-1987 (Boxes 1-4; 2.6 linear feet)
Series 3: Business and Financial Papers, 1940-1985 (Box 4; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, 1920, 1951-1987 (Box 4; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1940-1987 (Boxes 4-5; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 6: Art Work, undated (OV1; 1 item)
Series 7: Photographs, 1930s-1986 (Box 5; 0.1 linear feet)
The collection has not been re-filmed to reflect the above arrangement. In an effort to provide continued access to the existing microfilm, microfilm reel information was gathered from previous box and folder labels and is provided, where possible, in parentheses after folder titles in the container listing below. Unfilmed material has likewise been noted. Researchers should note that reel numbers have not been verified.
Related Material
Other resources in the Archives relating to Dorothy Dehner include oral history interviews with Dehner, October 1965 and December 1966, and a photograph of Dehner by Dena, 1966.
Separated Material
Originals of loaned material, including photographs of Dorothy Dehner and David Smith, sketchbooks, correspondence between Dehner and Smith, an inventory, and some printed material, were returned to Dehner after microfilming. Loaned material is available on reels D298 (portions), D298A, 1269 (portions) and 1472, but, not being part of the collection housed in the Archives, is not described in this finding aid.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects:
Smith, David, 1906-1965; Graham, John, 1881-1961; Philadelphia Art Alliance
Subjects-Topical:
Sculpture, Modern -- New York (State) -- New York; Women sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews; Art -- Economic aspects; Art -- Study and teaching
Types of Materials:
Interviews; Photographs; Sound recordings; Works of art
Names:
Willard Gallery
Provenance
The Dorothy Dehner papers were loaned and/or donated by the creator in several installments from 1967 to 1987 and were microfilmed in part on reels D298-D298A, 796, 829, 1269, 1372, 1472, and 3482. Some material lent for microfilming was never subsequently donated; loaned material is available on microfilm only and is not considered part of the actual collection housed in the Archives. The art work in the collection most likely belonged to Garnett McCoy originally, and was included in the collection during processing in 2005.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. research facility.
Alternative Forms Available
Microfilmed portions of the collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels D298-D298A, 796, 829, 1269, 1372, 1472, and 3482 at Archives of American Art offices, and for interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the material on microfilm. To aid researchers, an attempt has been made to note the corresponding reel number for each folder in the container listing below.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1935-1982 (bulk 1950s-1982), Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
  Series consists of scattered material shedding light on different aspects of Dehner's life and work. Included are some student papers dating from her time at Skidmore College in 1951-1952, including an essay on eighteen artists and the Metropolitan Art Museum written for extra credit and notes from a class she took on Oriental Cultures; various notes and lists created by Dehner consisting of information pertaining to her biography and career; the transcript and/or tapes of various interviews, including ones with K--- Osis, Herman Cherry, Judith McCandless, and ---- Rapp; a list of things that Dehner took with her when she left Bolton's Landing in 1951-1952; copies of selected clippings and typescript copies featuring press comments on Dehner's work in the mid- to late-1960s; proofs and copies of her biographical sketch in the publication, Who's Who; a photocopy of the honorary degree she received from Skidmore College; and miscellaneous personal papers, including recipes, notes, and a wedding announcement for her stepdaughter, Abby Mann Thernstrom. Also found here is some material relating to David Smith, including a chronology submitted for Dehner's review and bearing her editing marks, a copy of Smith's last will and testament, a letter of introduction for Smith from Audrey McMahon of the College Art Association (dating from their trip to Europe in the mid-1930s), and a name tag for Smith of unknown origin.
  Series is arranged alphabetically by document type.
  - Biographical and Career Information (Box 1)
    - (Reel 796), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - (unfilmed), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - David Smith Chronology (unfilmed), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Copies of Footnotes to Article on Dorothy Dehner (unfilmed), circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photocopy of Honorary Degree and Related Material (unfilmed), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Interviews (Box 1)
    - Transcript of Interviews with K--- Osis (Reel D298), 1963, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Tapes (unfilmed) (Box 1)
      - Dorothy Dehner Interviewed by Herman Cherry, 1973, (2 folders; 3 tapes including duplicates) (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
      - Dorothy Dehner Interviewed by Judith McCandless, 1973, (3 folders; 6 tapes including duplicates) (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
      - Dorothy Dehner Interviewed by ---- Rapp, 1981, (3 tapes) (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Dorothy Dehner Interviewed for "David Smith Documentary," undated, (3 tapes including duplicates) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Incomplete List of People Who Interviewed Dorothy Dehner (unfilmed), undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Copy of Last Will and Testament of David Smith (Reel 1269), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letter of Introduction for David Smith (Reel D298), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - List of Things Taken from Bolton Landing (Reel 1269), 1950s (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Name Tag for David Smith (Reel D298), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Notes (Box 1)
    - (Reel 796), undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - (unfilmed), undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Press Comment on the Work of the Artist (Reel 796), 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Recipes (Reel 796), undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Photocopy Reproductions of Art Work (Box 1)
    - (Reel 796), undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - (unfilmed), undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Sketch in Who's Who (Box 1)
    - (Reel 1269), undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - (unfilmed), undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Student Papers (Box 1)
    - Essay, "Survey of Eighteen Artists and [the Metropolitan Art Museum]" (Reel 1269), 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Notebooks, Notes from Class on Oriental Culture (unfilmed), 1951-1952, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Wedding Announcement for Abby Mann (unfilmed), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Correspondence, 1927-1987, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-4; 2.6 linear feet)
  Series consists of Dehner's personal and professional correspondence, comprised of mostly incoming letters but also some early drafts or copies of outgoing letters in addition to some enclosures such as loan agreements, shipping receipts, manuscripts, and printed material. Correspondents include museums, galleries, art dealers, curators, scholars, students, artists, writers, friends, and relatives. Correspondence largely documents her various personal and professional relationships, her efforts to promote and exhibit her artwork and to facilitate art historical research (on David Smith, herself, and other artists), and her various creative activities.
  Personal correspondents include David Smith, his sister, Catherine, and his mother, Golda; Smith's second wife, Jean Smith Pond, and his two daughters, Rebecca and Candida; Dehner's second husband, Ferdinand Mann and stepdaugher, Abby (Mann) Thernstrom; friends and fellow artists, Edgar and Lucille Corcos Levy, Herman Cherry, and Louise Nevelson; and her heart surgeon, Elliott Hurwitt, among others. Dehner often established friendships with individuals who started out corresponding on a professional basis (such as curators, dealers, and students), so personal correspondence can often be found interspersed with professional correspondence.
  Professional correspondence typically relates to the loan, exhibition, and sale of Dehner's work and the Smith work that Dehner owned - notably, to the traveling show of her work that Dehner organized in the early-1950s, to various group and solo shows (including ones at the Barbara Feidler Gallery, Philadelphia Art Alliance, Rutgers University, and Storm King Art Center, among others), and to her dealings with Mildred Constantine and Marian Willard (of the Willard Gallery), among others. Correspondence with curators, scholars, and students relates to research inquiries primarily about Smith, but also about Dehner herself and other artists of her era (such as John Graham, Irene Rice Pereira, and Louise Nevelson). Professional correspondence also concerns the editing and publication of the foreword she wrote for the re-issue of John Graham's System and Dialectics of Art, and the publication of her poems in the journal Tracks; certain matters pertaining to David Smith's estate, such as the disposition of certain items belonging to Dehner and the controversial alteration of the painted surfaces of certain Smith sculptures (which was carried out by one of the executors); donations of art works to various institutions, including Dehner's effort to raise funds from Jan Matulka's former students to purchase and donate one of his paintings to the Guggenheim Museum; and the donation of her papers to the Archives, and subsequent permissions to access and publish from them.
  Correspondence is typically arranged in alphabetical order according to name of correspondent. Letters from an individual correspondent are then arranged in folders according to the reel on which they were microfilmed or in a folder of "unfilmed" material, as the case may be. Some files contain the letters of various individuals and are arranged according to subject (e.g. "Various, Condolence Letters"). Letters from a correspondent with an unknown surname are arranged in a file according to first name, and unidentified letters and fragments are arranged in files at the end of the series. Related material can be found amongst business and financial papers.
  - A (Box 1)
    - (Reel D298), 1946-1966 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - (Reel 796), 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - (Reel 829), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - (Reel 1269), undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - (unfilmed), 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - A. M. Sachs Gallery (unfilmed), 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Abbeville Press (unfilmed), 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - American Federation of Arts (Reel D298), 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - American Society of Contemporary Artists (Box 1)
    - (Reel 796), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - (unfilmed), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Andre Emmerich Gallery (Box 1)
    - (Reel 796), 1969, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - (unfilmed), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Archives of American Art (Box 1)
    - (Reel D298), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - (Reel 796), 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - (Reel 829), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - (Reel 1269), 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - (Reel 1372), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - (unfilmed), 1977-1987 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Anita Aronoff (Box 1)
    - (Reel 796), undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - (Reel 1269), undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Art for Offices (Box 1)
    - (Reel 796), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - (Reel 1269), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Art Students League (Reel 1269), 1975, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Artists for CORE (later SEDF) (Box 1)
    - (Reel D298), 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - (Reel 796), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - (Reel 1269), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - (unfilmed), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Artists for Environment (See also Joel Levy) (Reel 796), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Associated American Artists (Box 1)
    - (Reel 796), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - (Reel 1269), 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - (unfilmed), 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Audubon Artists (Box 1)
    - (Reel D298), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - (Reel 796), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - (unfilmed), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - B (Box 1)
    - (Reel D298), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - (Reel 796), 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - (Reel 1269), 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - (unfilmed), 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - B. S. Livingston and Co. (unfilmed), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Barbara Feidler Gallery (unfilmed), 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Ellen Baum (unfilmed), 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - John I. H. Baur (Whitney Museum) (Reel D298), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Karen Bearor (unfilmed), 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Benson Gallery (unfilmed), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Berenice Steinbaum Gallery (unfilmed), 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - George Biddle (Box 1)
    - (Reel D298), 1960 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - (Reel 829), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - (Reel 1372), 1963, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - (unfilmed), 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Elizabeth Blake (Reel D298), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Bloomington-Normal Art Association (Reel D298), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Dan Budnik (Box 1)
    - (Reel 1269), undated (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - (Reel 1372), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - (unfilmed), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - C (Box 1)
    - (Reel D298), 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - (Reel 796), 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - (Reel 829), 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - (Reel 1372), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - (unfilmed), 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Canyon Road Art Gallery (Reel 829), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Herman Cherry (Box 1)
    - (Reel D298), 1948-1949, 1954-1965 (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - (Reel 796), 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - (Reel 1269), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 94)
    - (Reel 1372), 1970-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 95)
    - (unfilmed), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Peter Chinni (Box 1)
    - (Reel D298), 1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 97)
    - (Reel 1372), undated (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Ralph Colin (Box 1)
    - (Reel D298), 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 99)
    - (Reel 796), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Deanna Collingwood (unfilmed), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Jane Cone (See also Fogg Art Museum) (Box 1)
    - (Reel 796), undated (Box 1, Folder 102)
    - (Reel 829), undated (Box 1, Folder 103)
    - (Reel 1372), undated (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Mildred Constantine (See also Museum of Modern Art) (Box 1)
    - (Reel D298), 1947-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 105)
    - (Reel 796), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 106)
    - (Reel 829), 1967, 1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 107)
    - (Reel 1269), 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 108)
    - (Reel 1372), 1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 109)
    - (unfilmed), 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Margaret and Doug Crockwell (Box 1)
    - (Reel D298), 1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 111)
    - (Reel 796), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 112)
    - (Reel 1372), undated (Box 1, Folder 113)
    - (unfilmed), 1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Cummer Gallery of Art (Box 1)
    - (Reel D298), 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 115)
    - (Reel 796), 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - D (Box 1)
    - (Reel D298), 1952-1966 (Box 1, Folder 117)
    - (Reel 796), 1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 118)
    - (Reel 1269), 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 119)